Latifa: (unintelligible)
[2:188]  You shall not take each others' money dishonestly, nor shall you bribe the officials in order to take other people's money, sinfully and knowingly.
Dr. Khalifa: Whatever, it's up to you. If you want to stop and take it verse by verse.
Latifa: (unintelligible)
Latifa: To me, that's my understanding (unintelligible) we should not take each other's money.
Well, (unintelligible)
Again, some, sometimes people like to bribe other people for things that they want,
and they, then, they're doing these type of things in the man's eyesight,
and not really being aware that Allah is seeing it all.
And while they're stealing from the people, Allah is seeing (unintelligible)
So, Allah, says, do
[2:188]  ... not take each others' money dishonestly, ...
Latifa: or (unintelligible) bribe all that's (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, just, just put this in perspective. You said that God, God schemes.
Latifa: Okay, what I said...
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, you said, you said God will scheme against you, right?
Latifa: I'm saying like, okay, like me and you, and I,
say prayers to (unintelligible)
for five dollars, something like that.
And then, I may take these five dollars and go get me a pint of gin or something, or,
or go pay those lotteries or something like this.
But then, I might have told you that I needed something to eat, or something like that.
And so, to me, that's being dishonest.
And then also, if I understand what this verse is like,
if I will say things that something happened to me and I went to jail,
and
I needed to get out,
and I will pay the, the officials,
you know, like they think that I stole something from somebody or hurt somebody,
and then, I would pay the officials to get out of jail or bribe them,
"let me get, I'll give you fifty dollars or a hundred dollars if you let me out. Don't worry about those other people."
And then, they take it.
And so, I'm, I'm worried about these other people not hearing
and seeing me make this bribe with the judge or whomever,
whereas God is looking directly at both of us.
Or we're both going to be in trouble.
But most men, you know, people curious don't think like that.
They think that they're trying to hide it from men alone,
whereas God is looking at the thing on the (unintelligible)
because of they think they're (unintelligible) a lot of trouble.
Latifa: But that's my understanding.
Dr. Khalifa: Also, to put this in a, in terms that happened to,
what we're saying is that when you (unintelligible) God schemes,
you're, you're very correct,
in that you go to the market and you buy things and then,
you go and give the, that they,
Dr. Khalifa: what do you call the...
A woman: cashier.
Dr. Khalifa: cashier?
You give the cashier five dollars
and she thinks that you gave her twenty dollars.
Well, she gives you the change.
You bought things for two dollars and she gives you eighteen dollars back.
Because she thought you gave her twenty dollars,
when you really gave her five dollars.
Now, you have two choices. You can take the eighteen dollars and walk out,
in which case you are eating other people's money dishonestly,
because at the end of the day, she will count her money and
she will be short fifteen dollars.
Or you can give her the money back,
like the Quran tells you.
The Quran says, you give her the money back,
because I gave her only five dollars.
Now, when you said God schemes, it's because if you do walk out with the money,
you eat other people's money dishonestly.
That person, you, you don't make fifteen dollars.
You actually lose a lot more than the fifteen dollars.
Dr. Khalifa: Something else will happen where you lose a lot of money.
Latifa: And you may go home and, and on your way home, you get a ticket.
Dr. Khalifa: Right. For, for seventy dollars.
Latifa: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Speeding ticket.
Or worse yet, you get in an accident or something.
Because breaking God's law is very serious.
You know, the seriousness here is not just taking fifteen dollars.
You know, fifteen dollars is nothing.
But the serious matter is really disobeying God.
When, when He says, it's a commandment,
[2:188]  You shall not take each others' money dishonestly, ...
Dr. Khalifa: So, in that case, you return the money because God says you return the money, regardless of how much it is.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: Isn't (unintelligible)
A woman: but (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right, because it will cost you a lot more,
A woman: When I...
Dr. Khalifa: It will cost you a lot more than, than the price of the cigarettes.
A woman: But they, sometimes they charge more than they cost.
Dr. Khalifa: You'd rather better, it's better that you lose money than you gain money, because God never says (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible) but it wasn't, it wasn't my intention that (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, you better, you make sure that you are a victim rather than the aggressor, because God makes it up to you.
So, the Muslim is aware that when this happens, the people usually look at you like, like, (unintelligible)
you know, there are some honest people around here.
They don't realize that you'll return it because you're scared to death.
Because it will actually cost you a lot more,
because it is a lot smarter to give back the money.
It's a lot smarter, a lot cheaper.
And you make a lot more money than what you were gonna make.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A woman: Like we had a movie about someone who finds a hundred thousands of dollars,
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: Because they belong to somebody who worked very hard for them, or whatever.
Dean Mahmoud: I know someone who never returned it.
Dr. Khalifa: Oh, yeah.
A man: Some people have a real struggle, man.
Dean Mahmoud: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: This is a real test.
Dean Mahmoud: I...
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, Latifa. Back to you.
Dean Mahmoud: No, no.
Latifa: Ok, As far as, as far as the bribery, is that the type of bribery (unintelligible)
A woman: Yep.
Dr. Khalifa: Well, bribery was, we had a, a national case of bribery on the TV and the radio.
Dean Mahmoud: Yeah.
Dean Mahmoud: The senator
Dr. Khalifa: The head of the Teamsters Union was found guilty of trying to bribe a senator,
give him a few acres of land in Las Vegas.
Because, because they wanted the senator to oppose
deregulation of a trucking industry, which means
the drivers make a lot of money from you and me.
So that, this is why, when you read it, it says,
[2:188]  ... nor shall you bribe the officials in order to take other people's money, sinfully and knowingly.
So, what the Teamsters Union president wanted was to take the people's money sinfully and knowingly.
Because the deregulation of a trucking industry, make, made the trucking business cheaper for us, and less money for them.
Dr. Khalifa: That's a bribe.
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: Suppose it probably been in a society where
A man: the bribe was become
Dr. Khalifa: a way of life.
A man: (unintelligible)
A man: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
A man: If, if, if we don't bribe, you cannot get any where in your own life.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: Is it Haram (Prohibited) to bribe in that, in that case?
A man: Even though you couldn't...
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: (unintelligible) bribe
Dr. Khalifa: You shall not bribe. That's a commandment.
Dr. Khalifa: What, what a bribe does, you want a visa, for example, to leave the country and you can get it if you bribe, if you bribe.
Dean Mahmoud: But suppose staying in the country means they will kill you unjustly.
Dr. Khalifa: Now, Dean Mahmoud makes it very difficult.
Dean Mahmoud: Yes. Suppose you did not commit a crime,
Dean Mahmoud: and your enemies in the government are going to frame you, and you know it,
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dean Mahmoud: and you're given a chance to leave the country, but you have to give, let's say, 100 good Egyptian pounds.
If you do not give the 100 good Egyptian pounds, then you will allow other people to commit also injustice.
Dean Mahmoud: And then, if you die, who will feed your family, your children, and so on? I think it's a hard question.
Dr. Khalifa: I, I, I make a policy of not putting myself in a test when I don't need to. So, since it's a theoretical situation.
A man: But does bribery include when you are asked for payment for, for, say, a, a policeman to forget that you've done something wrong?
A man: Like in the Philippines, you know, the, the cops, you see, know, you know,
A man: for something, so I'm going to forget.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: There's also (unintelligible)
Dean Mahmoud: Especially on Christmas.
A man: Yeah.
Dean Mahmoud: Yes. On Christmas, the policeman tells you, you deserve this ticket.
A man: For the Christmas gift, I'm gonna forget.
Dean Mahmoud: Well, I said, I will pay for the ticket.
But you know, I said, never mind, the government is rich, but my family needs it.
Dean Mahmoud: So you (unintelligible)
A man: Cause I was planning on...
Dean Mahmoud: (unintelligible)
A man: Institutionalized, right.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: Like it's just almost a standard thing, where it's
A man: like going across the border or something and just...
Dr. Khalifa: Nobody, nobody's gonna get me to say, go ahead and bribe.
A man: Yeah.
A man: Just wrong.
Dr. Khalifa: The commandment is, you shall not bribe.
A woman: So, God made it, maybe a little easier because He says, you shall not bribe,
[2:188]  ... in order to take other people's money, sinfully ...
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
A woman: So, perhaps, the situation (unintelligible)
A woman: Don't ask about the things that you don't, that if you knew, would hurt you.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
But you see, the policeman, the policeman (unintelligible) will take a bribe in order to forget about the ticket.
Dr. Khalifa: Now, where does the ticket money go?
Dean Mahmoud: To the government.
Dr. Khalifa: Your ticket, right.
Your ticket goes to the general treasury, where some other people are gonna get the money, possibly salaries or whatever.
Dr. Khalifa: So, what you're doing, you're diverting the money from other sources.
A woman: But for the (unintelligible)
Dean Mahmoud: But that is different from the other case.
Dean Mahmoud: So, suppose you want to expedite your paper, that's something else.
You go again, I take Egypt again.
Dean Mahmoud: I don't want Egypt.
Dr. Khalifa: Ok. But you're not supposed to (unintelligible)
Dean Mahmoud: So, you are not giving money to,
Dean Mahmoud: you are not going to take away money from the government.
Dean Mahmoud: Government says, you must pay ten pounds for passport. All right.
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dean Mahmoud: Then, you see this hardworking man, and you tell him, "here is two pounds. Hurry up!"
Dr. Khalifa: Right. You know how he will hurry up?
Dean Mahmoud: Is that a bribe or is it a gift?
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, I'm gonna tell you how he will hurry up.
He's gonna put my papers on the side and take your paper and push it through.
So, my paper is gonna be delayed.
That's what happens.
He will give priority to your papers
Dr. Khalifa: by pushing my paper on the side or other people's papers on the side.
Dean Mahmoud: No, that's true.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, this will (unintelligible)
Dean Mahmoud: It will be at the expense of others.
Dean Mahmoud: But suppose he says, he will just wake up early and work, work extra.
Dr. Khalifa: No, and he will not do that.
He will just, he will push the other, the other people's papers on the side and he will put your paper on the top.
That's what they will do.
We must remember that there is a law of the Quran that says,
if you are forced by circumstance without being malicious or deliberate,
then you are not committing a sin.
So, God understands the circumstances but if you don't get a visa, they will kill you.
Now, that's self-defense.
You bribe, you do anything, you are forced.
You are forced by circumstance and you are not being malicious or deliberate,
and certainly you are not eating other people's money dishonestly.
So, God understands. It's a matter of, of common sense.
Dr. Khalifa: Islam is absolutely common sense.
A man: Alhamdu Lillah.
Dr. Khalifa: Do you have a question, Loretta?
Loretta: (unintelligible)
Loretta: It's so important (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Exactly.
Loretta: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: And there's no (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, back to Latifa.
Do Not Beat Around the Bush
[2:189]  They ask you about the phases of the moon! Say, "They provide a timing device for the people, and determine the time of Hajj pilgrimage." It is not righteous to beat around the bush by asking such irrelevant questions;* ...
[2:189]  ... But the righteous thing is to be straightforward and to observe God, that you may succeed.
(unintelligible) but then,
I, I think that seems to have a, a pretty high (unintelligible) that in itself.
But straightforward.
Okay, like, like (unintelligible) they're saying that, you know, like somebody asked you about the moon.
But then, Allah says, (unintelligible) they provided a timing device for the people.
Latifa: But that was, you know, that's (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, well, this really, this, this, they ask you, Muhammad, about the phases of the moon.
So, these people really came to him saying, you're, you're not a prophet.
So, instead of saying, you're not a prophet, they said, what, what is, what, what about the phases of the moon?
Tell us about the phases of the moon.
But that's not the real question.
The question is, prove to us that you are prophet of God.
Dr. Khalifa: So, they're beating around the bush.
Latifa: Okay, but, okay.
Dr. Khalifa: So, God is providing the answer to Muhammad here in this verse.
Latifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: And tell them that it is a timing device.
And it will tell us when to pass the month, which is the ninth month, and which is the twelfth month,
the time for Hajj.
We were looking at the moon today, and you can tell this is the second day of the month.
The new, a new lunar month.
You can tell by the fact that it, it rises early.
Now, it gets later and later, bigger and bigger, until it is a full moon on the fourteenth day of the month.
Dr. Khalifa: So, you can tell it's a timing device.
Latifa: Okay, but, you know, what, what, what, what I'm saying is like, (unintelligible), I'm not sure.
To me, okay, what I'm sure of is that it's saying to me.
Latifa: Now, people be straightforward. Do not beat around the bush (unintelligible)
Latifa: That's what it's saying to me, and that's what I do.
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Latifa: But then I have problems with that.
Because sometimes I'm too straightforward.
So, people tell me.
Latifa: And make (unintelligible) of whatever you're hurt.
Dr. Khalifa: That's very good or...
Latifa: And so, you know, because in society they say you should not make a (unintelligible) or whatever.
And you kind of hold some of it.
But I'm not like that. I'm being straightforward.
Latifa: Because that's (unintelligible) what comes up comes up.
Dr. Khalifa: That's good.
Latifa: And it hurts people's skeleton.
I don't mean to hurt nobody's skeleton just that I be straightforward.
If, you know, boy, I don't like your hair, I don't like your hair. Or, you know,
and I just say it.
And before you know, I've said it. This person is hurt.
And then, somebody come back and tell me, well, I think you should have said something else. You shouldn't have hurt their feelings.
(unintelligible), you know.
And then, that kind of looks like on me to make me,
Latifa: maybe I ain't reading it properly.
Latifa: So, is that supposed to be...
Dr. Khalifa: Well, you see that,
Dr. Khalifa: So, well, first of all, you have to be straightforward.
Dr. Khalifa: Now, (unintelligible)
Latifa: In any, any form, fashion or
Latifa: whatever?
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: Don't, don't beat around the bush
Latifa: Okay.
Dr. Khalifa: under any situation.
But, there are different ways of being straightforward. There's a diplomatic way.
(unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Doing it easy in mind.
Dr. Khalifa: So, the Quran says, invite to the way of the Lord by wisdom and tact.
Latifa: Okay.
Dr. Khalifa: And, and being diplomatic.
Dr. Khalifa: So, you can be straightforward.
Latifa: I mean, (unintelligible) different, different than
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. Instead of saying, I don't like your hair, you can say, you know, I like your hair better when it's up.
Latifa: Okay.
Dr. Khalifa: So, this is a positive, this is a positive statement.
Latifa: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: At the same time, you told the person, I don't like your hair this way.
Latifa: Okay.
Dr. Khalifa: But, but you said it in a diplomatic way. You're, you're straightforward. And you're telling the truth.
Dr. Khalifa: But, at the same time, you didn't hurt the person's feelings.
Latifa: Okay.
Latifa: So, be straightforward.
Rules of War*
[2:190]  You shall fight in the cause of GOD against those who fight you, but do not aggress for GOD does not love the aggressors.
I will try to explain so...
Latifa: I think (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Latifa: [2:191]  You may kill them if they attack you, and evict them from whence they evicted you. ...
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, Abdullah, she attacked you.
A woman: No.
A woman: For nothing. I saw the whole thing.
Dr. Khalifa: Masouda threw a pillow at Abdullah.
A woman: No. I (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Now, correction, correction. I have to, I have to correct that. She was trying to get Ahmad's attention.
Dr. Khalifa: She was trying to get Ahmad's attention to quiet down the children.
Dean Mahmoud: It was unintentional.
Dr. Khalifa: But Ahmad did not know part of it, so she threw a pillow at Ahmad.
But she missed.
And she got Abdullah.
Because Abdullah is always the recipient of these tricks.
The other day, the other day, Catherine wanted to trick Erol.
Dr. Khalifa: Erol had
Catherine: done terrible things
Dr. Khalifa: done terrible things to Catherine.
Catherine: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: So, Catherine went and got the shaving cream.
A cap of shaving cream.
And went to Erol's shoe and filled it up with shaving cream.
Dr. Khalifa: Except, it was not Erol's shoe. It was Abdullah's
A man: Oh, my.
A man: That was funny.
A woman: Brother Abdullah, he was so good about it. And he said, well that's alright, it happens all the time.
A woman: Oh, my (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: So, God knows that Abdullah can take it.
See, had, had, had Masouda got Ahmad, he would have turned right around and threw the pillow at her.
Throw the bigger pillow or something.
But Abdullah just put the pillow aside and smiled.
Dr. Khalifa: Bless his soul.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: I think he carried the shoe to the person. What's the meaning of this?
She had to explain that.
[2:190]  You shall fight in the cause of GOD against those who fight you, but do not aggress for GOD does not love the aggressors.
As you know, Iraq attacked Iran.
And they went on fighting each other even in the sacred months, months, where there is no war,
supposed to be no war.
Dr. Khalifa: And then, they claim they are Muslims.
A man: In sacred months?
Dr. Khalifa: The sacred, they're actually Haram.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Ramadan or Shawwal.
A man: Ramadan.
Dr. Khalifa: Rajab.
Rajab, Ramadan.
Zul-Hijjah, Muharram.
Almost.
Dr. Khalifa: Okay, 191.
Latifa: [2:191]  You may kill them if they attack you, and evict them from whence they evicted you. Oppression is worse than murder. Do not fight them at the Sacred Mosque (Masjid), unless they attack you therein. If they attack you, then you may kill them. And this would their just retribution.
Dr. Khalifa: Keep going.
A man: (unintelligible)
A woman: What's the (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: 192.
Latifa: [2:192]  However, if they refrain, then GOD is Forgiver, Merciful.
[2:193]  You may fight them to prevent oppression, and to practice GOD's religion in complete freedom. Once they refrain, there shall be no aggression except against the wicked.
[2:194]  If they attack you during the Sacred Months, then you may fight during the Sacred Months. Aggression may be met by an equivalent response. If they attack you, you may attack them to inflict equivalent retribution. You shall observe GOD and know that GOD is with those who observe Him.
[2:195]  Spend in the cause of GOD; do not throw yourselves with your own hands into disaster. You shall be charitable for GOD loves the charitable.
Okay, all that's really a separate thing to think, the laws that Allah has given us for the aggressors,
and talking about the sacred months, that we should not fight in the sacred months, but if somebody aggress us,
then we can fight them or kill them, or even give them the same, you know, amount of punishment that they give us,
no more, and no less, is said.
And I think somewhere else you can, (unintelligible) state that
Latifa: it would be better if you could forget them.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes, right. You see, again, again and again, it says, do not aggress, do not attack, only if they attack you.
Yet, the general belief in the world is that Islam is a religion of the swords, and aggressors, and,
and really you don't blame the people, because of what the so-called Muslims are doing.
But Islam, this is the real Islam in the Quran, cause you do not attack until they attack you.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A man: How about, because, there is a strong, some nations, you know, like Spain, and (unintelligible), and...
Dr. Khalifa: They don't aggress. They don't really aggress. When they went into Egypt and Syria, there was no war.
Dr. Khalifa: When they went to North Africa, there was no war. They didn't aggress.
A man: And the, when they went to
A man: Spain.
Dr. Khalifa: They aggressed. This is why they did all this to Spain.
Dr. Khalifa: Now, when they went to Spain, they went for other reasons, beside
A man: I think even in North Africa, they, they found some resistance of others.
A man: (unintelligible)
A woman: You talk to me?
A man: To Douglas, yeah.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Uh-oh
A woman: I thought (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible) Baruni (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Baruni and (unintelligible)
A man: Lydi.
Dr. Khalifa: Lydi.
Dr. Khalifa: So, it, as you see the verse is very clear that you do not aggress.
You take side of the weak.
But the, the instances where you fight is, are two things: if you are attacked or if you are oppressed,
religion-wise. Because the most precious thing, the most precious thing to us is our convictions, worshipping God alone.
Dr. Khalifa: And if there's anything (unintelligible) that will stop us from doing this, we have to fight to preserve it.
A woman: (unintelligible)
A woman: You know (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: Problems you mentioned earlier, like the transient problem, you know, that's oppression.
Even here in this city, they had the same thing as well.
They were even setting up tents, and the company that, the city council tear them down.
And the way it is now, the man has to break the law, (unintelligible)
A woman: We're not actually...
Dr. Khalifa: We're talking about religious oppression.
A woman: Ok.
Dr. Khalifa: Religious oppression.
Well, before I close, before we close, I want to mention that
the Zikr will be, we're gonna Pray in the morning at 6 o'clock,
and it is followed by the Arabic language lessons, and we are having a lot of fun, I'm telling you.
If you're not taking the Arabic lessons, you're missing a lot of fun.
And the students can testify to that.
Also, we have the best Arabic course in the whole world.
Just think, next week, Latifa will be reading Quran in Arabic.
That's right.
And she started, she started from zero.
This morning, we're gonna finish the alphabet in the, in the cursive, the way it is written in Quran.
Dr. Khalifa: So, a week from today, I promise you, Latifa will be reading Quran in Arabic.
A woman: Alhamdu Lillah.
Dr. Khalifa: And this is how good the Arabic, our course is.
Latifa: IN SHAA ALLAH. IN SHAA ALLAH.
Latifa: IN SHAA ALLAH
Dr. Khalifa: IN SHAA ALLAH
Dr. Khalifa: Don't worry Latifa. Yeah. I must say IN SHAA ALLAH.
Latifa: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: Address your heart. Yes. This is a Quranic injunction.
Dr. Khalifa: We must say IN SHAA ALLAH. So, a week from today, IN SHAA ALLAH,
Dr. Khalifa: Latifa will be reading the Quran in Arabic. And you will witness that.
A woman: Oh, what's the meaning?
A woman: Are you going to teach this?
Dr. Khalifa: Yes. We're gonna, then we'll, this is why she's gonna read, but she will not know the meaning of it.
A woman: Sorry.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes. This is only two weeks.
Dr. Khalifa: Now the meaning...
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right. Of course. Yes.
But when you read the word Quran in Arabic, you understand what it is talking about.
You wanna read words like Allah and, there are already some words that you know.
Okay, we're gonna close, Pray Al-'Eshaa, and then we'll go home and sleep and come back at 6 o'clock, IN SHAA ALLAH.
Al-Fãtehah
Bism Allah Arrahman Arraheem (1:1)
Al hamdu Lillahi Rabbil ‘Alameen (1:2)
Arrahman Arraheem (1:3)
Maliki Yawm Eddeen (1:4)
Eyyaka Na’abudu Wa Eyyaka Nasta’aeen (1:5)
Ehdina Al-Serata Al-Mustaqeem (1:6)
Serata Al-Lazeena An’amta ‘Alayhim Ghayri Al-Maghdoobi ‘Alayhim Wa Laddaalleen (1:7)
Dean Mahmoud: Where is Erol?
Dr. Khalifa: Well, Erol is in California.
Dean Mahmoud: Hmm? Ah, he is with his parents, his mother.
Dean Mahmoud: Very good.
Dr. Khalifa: But a verse we look at 11:114, it gives the same meaning, so,
apparently, Salat is also another means of, of wiping out sins.
Dr. Khalifa: Now, I would say those are the unperceivable sins.
A man: What is the word we used today?
Dr. Khalifa: Inadvertent?
A woman: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: Inadvertent sins.
Dr. Khalifa: Like you, you tell (unintelligible) inadvertently,
like, oh, I love your dress, when you really hate it.
This is an inadvertent, inadvertent sin.
So, the Prayers will take care of those.
Dr. Khalifa: I shouldn't put (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Oh, I'm sure any of the, of the positive practices.
You know, there's a reason for them.
God gave us a prescription, the Salat, Zakat charity, the Fasting. I'm sure all these things.
Dr. Khalifa: I mean, fasting is a form of self-imposed suffering, isn't it?
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: And it is worship at the same time, and therefore, I'm sure it wipes sin.
So, we do it hoping that this will clean our record.
But the idea that, that we learn from the Adam and Eve lesson
is that we cannot be in Heaven with one sin.
And God picked out a very simple sin, you know,
it's eating from the tree, bite of apple, you know, you're out.
I mean, I mean, it's not, it's not really a bite of apple, but if you think of it this way, as it's, as it's commonly believed,
it's a very simple act of disobedience, and you're out.
Dr. Khalifa: So, this teaches us, yes sir.
Dean Mahmoud: Very good, I'll come to that.
Dean Mahmoud: If the verse also says that it is...Uh-oh, I lost it again. It is not on that page that...
Dr. Khalifa: Yes. 29:45
Dean Mahmoud: 29:... If it's the means
Dr. Khalifa: for remembering God, yes.
Dean Mahmoud: There's another.
Dean Mahmoud: If it is any the means for remembering God, which is even greater, so,
Dr. Khalifa: That's right.
Dean Mahmoud: So, if it's the means for remembering Allah, we can also say that Salat is a technique against forgetting,
Dean Mahmoud: which means, therefore, Salat might be the technique that we will not fall into the sin of
Dr. Khalifa: Adam and Eve.
Dean Mahmoud: of Adam.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible) God. Yes.
Dean Mahmoud: So, it prevents us from eating from that tree.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dean Mahmoud: I think these things are all connected with...
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, actually, in one of the statements, at least one, in the Quran, that says, Adam and Eve forgot.
Dean Mahmoud: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: So, they forgot God, and Prayer makes you remember God.
Now, how many common people think of God, you know?
How often do they think of God?
They wake up in the morning, and they're going to work.
They get up in the morning, and they are hating it,
and they go shaving or making up their faces, and
putting their faces on, as they say.
And then, and then go to work.
They never think of God.
Dr. Khalifa: And then, at the end of the day, back home, referring generally.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: So, most people don't think of God whatsoever.
They forget.
What's remind me, a commandment in Sura 59, verse 18,
59:18, let's look at it.
Dr. Khalifa: It's one on this subject.
A woman: Page 392.
Dr. Khalifa: 392. 18, it says,
[59:18]  O you who believe, beware of GOD, and let each of you examine what he or she had advanced for the coming Day. You shall observe GOD, for GOD is Cognizant of everything you do.
[59:19]  Do not be like those who forgot GOD, so He made them forget their own souls. These are the wicked.
[59:20]  Not equal are those who have deserved Hell and those who have deserved Heaven; those who have deserved Heaven are the winners.
So, it says,
when people forget God, God makes them forget themselves.
Dr. Khalifa: So, they neglect themselves.
A woman: Who?
Dr. Khalifa: And who, who is themselves?
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible) is their souls.
They forget to feed their soul.
A lot of people are very careful in the morning to get a cup of tea or breakfast.
So, they're giving their body their cup of, of coffee or, or breakfast.
And if they don't, do not breakfast to eat, they never forget lunch.
So, they don't forget their body, which is not them.
The body is a garment worn by them,
(unintelligible) for a blink of an eye.
This whole life is like a blink of an eye, even it's not that.
Because in, in the real life, in the Hereafter, we're talking in terms of millions of years.
So, what is 60 years or 100 years?
The blink of an eye.
Yet, people put all their concentrations
on this blink of an eye.
Are they gonna be rich or poor,
tall or short,
fat or skinny.
Yes.
In a blink of an eye.
And they are concentrating all their efforts on that blink of an eye.
When it's really not important at all to be tall or short, man or woman, fat or skinny,
beautiful or ugly.
It really doesn't matter.
The blink of an eye.
What matters, this blink of an eye is very important in that it prepares you for the, for the Hereafter.
So, our goal is, is to go out in this life sinless.
I don't know if Sammy and Beth missed that, but Rahima just added
Dr. Khalifa: that the, there are verses in Quran that says that the Salat Prayer wipes out sins also, another way of wiping out sins.
A woman: Is Fasting (unintelligible)?
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, fasting, (unintelligible), all the duties, all the duties imposed on you by God,
wipe out, will wipe out your sins.
Because that verse we looked at in 11:114 is a general statement that the righteous works wipe out sins.
[11:114]  ... righteous works ...
Dr. Khalifa: When you feed a hungry person out on the street, that wipes some of your sins.
A woman: You know, I, I talked (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Fast in Ramadan.
A woman: Fast in Ramadan.
You know, when (unintelligible) you feel kind of grubby,
A woman: but you do see a fasting person (unintelligible) clean your sight.
A woman: (unintelligible).
Dr. Khalifa: I don't know if it's fasting outside of Ramadan.
A woman: (unintelligible)
A man: What if I to wake up for the (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: It's like...
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
A man: Otherwise, no.
A man: So, the tradition of, of Monday and Thursday that a Hadith (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Monday and Thursday? Yeah, that's a Hadith.
A man: Yeah, that's what I, what I...
Dr. Khalifa: Just like in Wudu (Ablution), Wudu, four things, but they do nine things.
I don't go for that. I go to, to what God says.
I don't wanna be (unintelligible) of God says.
Dr. Khalifa: God says, fast the month of Ramadan.
A man: Extra fasting is not good.
Dr. Khalifa: No, it doesn't.
A man: But, but, but, fasting the number of days you miss (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
A man: (unintelligible)
A woman: If fasting has any effect (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right, right. That,
A woman: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: If it is stated in the Quran, yes.
A woman: (unintelligible) but did you see...
Dr. Khalifa: Like if you break an oath, you have to fast three days.
That's, these are, these are obligatory.
Dr. Khalifa: They are stated in the Quran, but you just, just fast on your oath.
A man: So if you fasted all of Ramadan and you have no fast to do, you wanna fast an extra day, it's not good to do that.
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
God says, fast a specific number of days.
It's like saying, when you make your Wudu, you do these four things.
So, Satan wants you to disobey God in any way or form.
So, if you want to fast, go on a diet, in other words, for health reason,
I will deliberately break my fast.
Dr. Khalifa: I will go on a diet and I will eat a date, or a peanut, or something, just to, so I will not be fasting, I'll be dieting.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: So, Satan's object is to make us break God's law.
A man: I mean, it's hard enough to fast for 30 days.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: (unintelligible) No, it's very, still a very common practice among, among the Sunni Muslims to, to fast on, on Monday and Tuesday.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, all kinds of...
Dr. Khalifa: And the three white days.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: If fasting is righteous, then I don't understand it's,
it's just like, well, God says in the Quran to do the five Prayers,
and I don't feel that if you did more than five,
A man: you did extra prayers, you would be fine.
A man: I mean, they're not doing it just to...
Dr. Khalifa: You're doing it...
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, you do it without limitations there.
A man: Because of a Hadith or...
Dr. Khalifa: You do it without limitations.
A man: Well, if you do it just because you feel like doing it,
Dr. Khalifa: that's the different. The Quran says that.
The Quran says, you can pray extra prayers, but doesn't say fast extra fasting.
That's just where the difference is and,
that as far as extra prayers are concerned, God says do them.
You get up in the middle of the night and pray.
But there are no limitations, no specific numbers.
And you have to do it because you feel like it.
And you are rewarded for that.
So, the Quran leads specifically for this and says, go ahead and do extra Salat Prayer.
Dr. Khalifa: But never says do extra fasting.
A man: Well, it says a specific number of days.
Dr. Khalifa: Right. For as far as fasting says, fast a specific number of days.
Dean Mahmoud: I think to be more exact, after you say in your translation, on specified days.
Dr. Khalifa: Exactly.
Dean Mahmoud: Specified days.
Dean Mahmoud: The month. Ramadan.
Dr. Khalifa: Or the month of Ramadan.
Dr. Khalifa: There's, there's the moon, the new moon, meaning the month of Ramadan, and the new moon is the next month.
Dr. Khalifa: Done and...
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: Right. Exactly.
They're just making it up.
Dr. Khalifa: And exactly the same. I don't think it is Ramadan.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Right.
You say, I'm gonna quit smoking,
and pledge to God, I'm gonna quit smoking.
Dr. Khalifa: And then, then, you don't.
A woman: (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible) with God (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: No, it's a pledge, it's a pledge to God.
A man: That's a question, whether it is a pledge to God or whether
if you say you're gonna do something where you don't do it, (unintelligible)
A man: I'm gonna do the laundry tomorrow. I don't do it for fun.
Dr. Khalifa: Or a promise to somebody.
A man: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: You're supposed to fulfill your promises to anybody.
A man: But if you don't, for some reason, fulfill a promise, is that something you, you'll have to fast for or (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, No.
A man: But only when you say, God, I'm gonna do something or...
Dr. Khalifa: I pledge.
If it is a pledge to God, then you have to fast three days or feed ten pour people.
(unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: Because God's Merciful, symbolically, don't get, like, more credit for your deeds than He would take away for a sin.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes, that's right.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: When you do a good deed, you're rewarded for ten.
Dr. Khalifa: When you do a bad deed, it's recorded as one sin.
A woman: But (unintelligible)
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Pardon?
A man: That's a number you've given.
Dr. Khalifa: No, no, no. The Quran says that.
A man: And one?
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: Really?
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A woman: (unintelligible)
See, God says,
Dr. Khalifa: God says, you do one good work and I'll give you reward for ten.
A man: Ten points.
Dr. Khalifa: But if you do a bad work, you'll be punished for one.
So, you are to pay for it here, if you commit,
if you go drink now, for example,
you will have to pay for, for the wine of friends.
Because you know it is, it is wrong.
But if you feed a hungry person on the street,
you get the rewards of feeding ten.
When you do one Salat, it's equivalent to ten.
You get the rewards for ten.
So,
the,
Dr. Khalifa: the only unforgivable offense is idol worship.
A man: They had to get catch phrase (unintelligible) so discouraging, you know, saying that (unintelligible) your life out sinning.
Dr. Khalifa: Yep.
A man: You know, but now the good came to (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: See?
A man: It's not (unintelligible) people to sin, though, I don't think so.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, but, but,
see,
the people who are in idol worship,
they do not have the advantages of forgiveness.
The disbelievers and the idol worshipers do not have the advantages of forgiveness,
or repentance.
So,
like I mentioned this before,
that this, this
monk was telling that says,
Dr. Khalifa: Believers are not better, they are just forgiven.
A man: But you can repent on idol worship, don't you?
Dr. Khalifa: Oh, yeah, oh, yeah.
You can repent from idol worship, as long as you are alive.
Dr. Khalifa: And now, when you're talking about idol worship and a person who died as an idol worshiper.
A man: Right.
Dr. Khalifa: That, that person is, is hopeless.
Dr. Khalifa: His sins are not forgiven. Yes.
A woman: I'm asking a question, because I'm not sure if it's in Quran or (unintelligible)
as far as (unintelligible),
well, if you wanna do something wrong, and then you don't do it,
you get rewarded, (unintelligible)
Is that (unintelligible)
a bad (unintelligible)
and you decide not to do it,
change your mind, and then
A woman: get the reward.
Dr. Khalifa: I, I, I don't think so. I don't remember it.
A man: What, what, what if I say, what if I say I'm gonna go down and get drunk, you know, and then I say, no, I can't do that.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: Then, I stay away from it.
Do I get anything extra for that?
A man: It sounds like a Hadith to me.
Dr. Khalifa: What you get is, you prevented the minus from going into your record.
A man: What you want to know is...
Dr. Khalifa: You saved yourself from punish, from severe punish.
A man: (unintelligible)
A woman: Yeah, but that's why I
A woman: want to (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: This is a Hadith, I know that.
But I was thinking that there are lots of things in Hadith that are also in Quran.
Dr. Khalifa: So, I have, I have to think about it.
A man: But we do get credit for that, because we're passing another test.
A man: But the test is funny.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes, yes, you can say that, yeah.
Dean Mahmoud: It's (unintelligible), I think.
A man: (unintelligible), yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: See, what you, what you're doing, your body wants to go and get drunk or whatever,
and, and you told your body, no, don't do that.
So, you're exercising your soul.
Your soul is becoming stronger, and your body is becoming your slave.
Dr. Khalifa: It's the other way around.
A man: So, your, your thought and action, your thought is like (unintelligible), your action is like (unintelligible).
Dr. Khalifa: That's right. You'll be surprised how many tests people put themselves into.
A lot of times we, we give ourselves tests when we really don't need to.
"What would you do if you were in that position?"
Dr. Khalifa: I said (unintelligible)
A woman: (unintelligible) I don't know.
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
A woman: (unintelligible)
A woman: So, (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: Well, yeah, there are thoughts that are wrong.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: So, the, the believers have the advantage of forgiveness and repentance.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yes.
Dr. Khalifa: Where sins are converted into credits.
A woman: Yeah.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, but...
A woman: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, here's, here's the verse, let's look at it.
Dean Mahmoud: But the...
Dr. Khalifa: I had to write it up, you know.
Ok.
25:70
[25:70]  ... Then, GOD will change their sins into credits. For GOD is Forgiving, Merciful.
Let us say you're in a state of idol worship for 10 years.
And you're, you commit sins and you repent.
But you cannot be forgiven (unintelligible).
And then all of a sudden, you come to the realization that you should not be an idol worshiper,
and you come out of idol worship, then all your sins will be forgiven and converted to credits.
We just, we should take this verse at face value,
just go to...
This is the description of the believers
63, let's start at 63, page 249, starting at 63, this,
[25:63]  And for the servants of God, Most Gracious who walk on earth humbly, and when the ignorant speak to them, they only utter peace.
[25:64]  And who spend the night before their Lord prostrating and standing.
[25:65]  And who say, "Our Lord, spare us the agony of Gehenna; surely, its retribution is agonizing.
[25:66]  "It is a miserable abode; a miserable destiny."
[25:67]  And when they spend, they are neither extravagant, nor stingy; they are moderate.
[25:68]  And they never set up besides GOD any idols, nor do they kill anyone except in the course of justice. Nor do they commit adultery. Anyone who does these is wicked.
[25:69]  The retribution will be doubled for them on the Day of Resurrection, and they abide therein in eternal humiliation.
[25:70]  As for those who repent, believe, and work righteousness, then GOD will change their sins into credits. For GOD is Forgiving, Merciful.
[25:71]  Whoever repents and works righteousness, GOD redeems him; a complete redemption.
So, all these are good news for us.
In other words, the, the fact that you have to go out of this life sinless is not a, a formidable and impossible thing.
In fact, it's attainable by the believers.
You just have to bear in mind that you continuously repent.
Just be ready to go anytime, and make sure that you are sinless.
Repenting all the time.
And if you are to fall in sin, be, be ready to pay.
Dr. Khalifa: If you think it is wrong and you're gonna do it anyway, be ready to pay.
Dean Mahmoud: I would like to suggest also, maybe that,
the way this word is conjoined,
the phrase "work righteousness" is conjoined with repentance.
With, in 17:71,
maybe the suggestion I'm offering is that,
suppose you harm someone,
and therefore you have disobeyed Allah,
and you ask Allah for forgiveness for what you have done,
still this might not be enough.
You have to work righteousness.
Dean Mahmoud: You might have to make amends regarding the person whom you have
Dr. Khalifa: Yes, you, you have hurt. Yes.
Dean Mahmoud: hurt.
Dean Mahmoud: Because I know the Quran is always puts belief and work
Dr. Khalifa: together.
Dean Mahmoud: always together.
Dr. Khalifa: Exactly.
Dean Mahmoud: This is not an isolated thing.
Dr. Khalifa: No, no, (unintelligible)
Dean Mahmoud: It's always all over its own.
Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: That's right.
Dean Mahmoud: Because I, I do remember, years ago,
that this problem was discussed in our country.
And our teacher, one of, one of the strict men, he said
if you insult a man,
later on he regrets, and you say, Allah,
I'm sorry I insulted him.
Our teacher used to say,
if that man really is repentant,
and if he meant what he said, (unintelligible) Allah
I'm sorry that I insult this man.
He should go to this man and apologize.
Dean Mahmoud: And, and that's still doing what Allah wants him to do.
Dr. Khalifa: That's right.
Dean Mahmoud: So, there is the social, the social aspect.
Dr. Khalifa: This, this whole discussion also brings into focus the importance of the duties,
the, the Salat, the Hajj.
Why should we save money and make the trip to Mecca and go through the hardships?
Also, the five Prayers a day, and the fasting of Ramadan.
Obviously those are,
God is trying to help us wipe out all the sins.
It's another answer to the question, why do we Pray five times a day.
Because of the inadvertent things that we do all the time.
Because of the laziness that we may exhibit.
Because of the things that we cannot help.
So, all the, the Prayers and fasting and these things
provide us with the means of erasing the sins.
But you, you see, when you go to Heaven,
you will not have all those sins that you attained, though, no more.
You will not have any record. Unless you do a personal investigation in your own that you yourself see.
You wanna (unintelligible) go back and review your life, and look to death,
you'll do it.
You can do it if you want,
but nobody answers you,
Dr. Khalifa: because, you, the faith is erased.
A woman: (unintelligible) the body (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: It's whatever you want, see.
In Heaven, you get anything you want.
If you want to look back and review your life,
only you can do it.
If you don't want anybody else to see it, only you, you decide that.
You're gonna, gonna win the Kingdom of God.
God says you do whatever you want.
There's absolutely no embarrassment, no humiliation.
There's always, there's nothing but dignity, and happiness, and love, and
perfect,
it's perfection,
and more than perfect in Heaven.
So, these are the means of editing the faith,
repentance,
and righteous works.
Okay, back to our lesson,
Sammy and Beth were in page 21,
verse 196,
which is talking about Hajj pilgrimage.
And I was explaining the things that you do.
Again, like all the other practices,
it's a form where you are
enforcing your mastership over your body.
Because,
with the vast majority of people,
the body is the boss.
They do everything in this life to please the body, to give it a good job, good money,
good house, good spouse.
The body, whatever, they cater to the body's desire.
That's all they want.
That's all they do.
And it is the most stupid thing
anybody can (unintelligible)
because the body vanishes,
becomes dust.
And then, you stand by yourself.
You know, people, you can imagine the person after shaving the body, they say,
my God, I spent all my life caring for this thing, which is rotting now.
Spent, I went to school,
and took tests,
to get a good degree,
and have a good job.
I just spent my life caring for this thing.
What did I do for myself?
Now, what you do for yourself
is the spiritual food, the Prayers, the Fasting,
the Hajj, righteous works, worshiping God, remembering God.
Because your soul is part of that.
[2:196]  ... But if you are ill, or suffering some head injury (then you may cut your hair), and expiate by fasting, or giving a charity, or some other form of worship. During the normal times of peace, if you break the state of sanctity between 'Umrah and Hajj, then expiate by offering a sacrifice. ...
When we were making Hajj, my father wanted to break the,
it's called Ihraam,
between 'Umrah and Hajj
Because (unintelligible) we were there early.
We were there on the first day of the, of the month,
Zul-Hijjah.
And, then the day,
the official day of Hajj is the eighth day,
everybody must be in Mecca, on the eighth day.
That, this is the day of Hajj,
the eighth of Zul-Hijjah.
On the ninth day, everybody must be on Mount 'Arafaat.
So, we went on the first, to finish the 'Umrah, on the first.
Now, we have eight days,
and my father wanted to relax,
change his clothes, shave, whatever he wanted to do.
So, he had to sacrifice a sheep.
And this is what this, this verse says.
I chose not to break the...
It's alright. (unintelligible) I'm sorry.
A man: (unintelligible)
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah.
A man: When you go to Ka'aba, is it the requirements, like this,
as stated in Quran, you have to go to 'Arafaat and
A man: circle the Ka'aba.
Dr. Khalifa: Well, most of the practices came to us like Salat through Abraham,
through,
but actually, most of the Hajj is mentioned here,
like, the encircling of the Ka'aba is mentioned here.
The, the,
Dr. Khalifa: running till Safa and Marwah is mentioned here.
Dean Mahmoud: And 'Arafaat is also 198.
Dr. Khalifa: Pardon?
Dean Mahmoud: 'Arafaat is mentioned in verse 198.
Dr. Khalifa: 198?
Dean Mahmoud: Yes, and Muzdalifah.
Dr. Khalifa: And Muzdalifah is mentioned
Dean Mahmoud: 198.
Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, that's right. 'Arafaat is mentioned.
[2:198]  ... When you come from 'Arafaat, ...
So, 'Arafaat is mentioned. Muzdalifah is mentioned.
So, almost everything in Hajj is mentioned in Quran.
Now, when you go around the Ka'aba seven times,
it will, will seem like idol worship.
So, you're going around the building.
And the people will raise the question, "are you worshiping this thing?"
And this is why the language of the Quran is very important here in Arabic where God says,
it is perfectly alright to go around the Ka'aba. This is how it says it.
You are not committing a sin by encircling the Ka'aba.
This is how, in fact, Ahmad Baruni raised that question the other day about the Safa and Marwah.
The language of Quran is very,
it's like God said it's perfectly alright for you to fall prostrate before Adam to the angels.
Are they worshipping Adam or what?
So, it is by permission from God
that you're doing this. You're doing this because in obedience to God.
And the angels fell prostrate before Adam not because they worshipped Adam, but in obedience to God.
And
this language of the Quran is very, very careful and very significant.
So, if anybody tells you that this is a form of idol worship, you say, it's an order from God. And God says it's alright.
That's the specific words of Quran as we are not committing a sin by,
Dr. Khalifa: let me see a, a good example here.
A man: It's in verse 203.
Dr. Khalifa: 203
[2:203]  You shall commemorate GOD during the specified days after Hajj; thus, you complete in less than two days, you commit no error, and if you stay longer, you commit...